

Email: <a href="mailto:consultant@londonresearchinternational.com">consultant@londonresearchinternational.com</a> www.LondonResearchInternational.com

# Mr. Edgar

**NATIONALITY: South Africa** 

## **SUMMARY**

<u>Consulting Experience</u>: Agri-Cultiva: Angola- developing different aspects of farming for the Angolan Government.

<u>D1 Oils</u>- Madagascar, Zambia, Swaziland, Mozambique- Development of bio-fuels within these countries.

<u>Principe Island</u>- Developing Cocoa plantations for the Mark Shuttle worth Foundation. Bosch Engineering: Development of sugar Estates in Tanzania.

Agri-Cultiva- Development of 3000ha of Banana Plantations, Angola.

#### **EDUCATION**

- 1991: Senior Certificate, Weston Agric College
- 1996: Certificate Public Relations, Du Toit & Agency
- 1996: Game Farm management, Fagasa 1+2
- 2006: Project Management Diploma, DMT Seminars
- 2010: Certificate Presentation Skills Course, Management Training Consultants
- 2010: Senior Certificate in Sugar management, SASA

## EMPLOYMENT RECORD/PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# • 2012- current: Demeter Farms, Malawi

# **General Manager**

General Manager for Developing 5000ha of sugar lands Co-Engineering of 126000L Ethanol Plant

Managing Developing Contractors



Email: consultant@londonresearchinternational.com

www.LondonResearchInternational.com

Overseeing 7 sections Managers

Overseeing workshops

Producing Budgets and managing the Financing department.

Managing 450 Farm Labour's.

Reporting to the directors and doing presentations

## • 2010-2012: South African Sugar Research Institute, South Africa

#### **Extension Specialist**

- Plan and implement extension strategy in consultation and co-operation with the RD&FCs
- ➤ Identify individual grower problems, and provide the appropriate extension and advisory packages to enable long-term solutions.
- ➤ Ensure prompt response to growers' requests to assess problems and follow up with appropriate recommendations.
- Ensure optimum use of newsletters, the Link and Ingede, field days, study groups and demonstrations to transfer SASRI technology.
- Provide specific advisory packages according to grower needs that include economic benefits where appropriate.
- Analyse mill data to provide growers with information on their productivity and cane quality.
- ➤ Organise and co-ordinate ERAs and appropriate follow-up assistance in the implementation of specialist advice.
- Promote of the use of SASRI technical services (e.g. FAS) and provide assistance to growers to interpret and make management decisions based on these inputs. Provide specific advisory packages according to grower needs that include economic benefits where appropriate.
- Analyse mill data to provide growers with information on their productivity and cane quality.
- Organise and co-ordinate ERAs and appropriate follow-up assistance in the implementation of specialist advice.
- Promote of the use of SASRI technical services (e.g. FAS) and provide assistance to growers to interpret and make management decisions based on these inputs.
- Prepare monthly, annual and ad hoc written reports for SASRI, and make presentations at staff meetings.



 $Email: \underline{consultant@londonresearchinternational.com}$ 

www.LondonResearchInternational.com

- > Source and collate regular up-dates on progress in research programmes and participate in the preparation of new or amended current recommendations.
- ➤ Participate in determining research priorities and grower needs in consultation with the RD&ECs leading to the formulation of the SASRI Programme of Work
- Organise a regular visit by the Director and specialists to each area.
- Organise groups of growers to visit SASRI.
- ➤ Identify themes for the road show, SASRI Grower Day, and local grower field days participate in the annual road show.
- Attend regional extension meetings.
- > Attend the Extension Indaba.
- ➤ Attend SASTA/present papers
- Participate in local committees; provide technical advice and follow-up action as appropriate.
- ➤ Participate in the following committees: Research Development and Extension, Local Pest & Disease Variety Control, Local Environment, Mill Cane Committees, Local Grower Councils.
- ➤ Attend the SASA P&D Steering committee AGM.
- > Implement SuSFarMS EMS model
- Implement new self audit system
- Carry out random audits by Eco-Zone
- Help with identified development projects.
- Work with SSG ES
- > Implement IPMS on all farms
- Monitor progress of IPMS on Eldana farms
- Understand organic fertilisers
- ➤ Develop a land usage plan for the area highlighting conservation areas, wetlands. Arable land based on the Eco-Zones.
- > Develop a unified EMS for all agricultural enterprises
- ➤ A GIS capable of providing all relevant information regarding sugarcane production from field level.
- ➤ All growers have land use plans.

### • 2004-2010: Energem, Lda, Mozambique

**Operations Manager** 



Email: <a href="mailto:consultant@londonresearchinternational.com">consultant@londonresearchinternational.com</a>
<a href="mailto:www.LondonResearchInternational.com">www.LondonResearchInternational.com</a>

- Overseeing development of 2000ha of jatropha for the bio fuels industry.
- Overseeing the development of 1000ha Castor Oil plantation.
- > Developing the infrastructure for the project.
- Managing and creating budgets.
- Overseeing all labour issue's as well as HR functions.
- > Implementing systems (finiance, HR,) as per mozambiqian law.
- Overseeing the importation of logistics onto the project.
- Managing a farm management team consisting of 5 farm managers, a nursery manager as well as the admin sector.
- Managing the bush clearing through to the planting of the jatropha plant.
- > Handling all timetables handed out to consultants.
- 1997-2003: DUNA VISTA SUGAR ESTATES, Mozambique Project Manager
- 1994-1997: BUSH LANDS SUGAR FARMS, Hluhluwe
   Assistant Farm Manager

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS	
n/a	
PUBLICATIONS	
n/a	
LANGUAGES	

English, Afrikaans (Basic), Zulu (Conversational), Shangaan (Basic), Portuguese (Basic)